Dorothy Marsh Papers, circa 1911-1973
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Dorothy Marsh Papers
circa 1911-1973
Marsh, Dorothy, 1899-1979
100
4 boxes (1.5 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Travel specialist and tour guide; and Red Cross official, World War II. The Collection includes correspondence, printed material, press articles, photographs, and memorabilia relating to Marsh's travel agency, Marsh Tours, Inc. Also correspondence and reports from Dorothy's work as a Red Cross teacher in Budapest, 1925, and as Regional Director of Red Cross Service Clubs during World War II; and material on the New York Women's Council and International Executive Service Corps.
Dorothy Marsh was born in Des Moines, Iowa in 1899. In 1927 she established Marsh Tours, Inc. in New York City with her sister Marjorie Marsh Enfield. The agency specialized in college tours and student travel. They later opened offices in London and Paris. Marsh was the travel advisor to Smith College to Europe, Asia, and other regions, handling arrangements for Junior Year Abroad trips, and other groups. During World War II, Marsh volunteered at the American Hospital in Paris for the French Red Cross. She served as the regional director of Red Cross Service Clubs with the Overseas Task Force manager and was stationed in North Africa, France, and Germany. She volunteered with the International Executive Service Corps (an "executive Peace Corps" to underdeveloped nations) in Bangkok in 1970, and East Malaysia in 1971. Her other accomplishments included embarking upon a special teaching mission for Red Cross in Budapest from 1925 to 1926; managing the American Women's Club in Paris from 1926 to 1927; being secretary to Air Attache, U.S. Embassy, Paris, 1923 to 1934; and membership in the New York Women's Council from 1959 to 1969. Dorothy Marsh died in 1979.
The Marsh Papers include correspondence, printed material, articles, photographs, and memorabilia relating to the career of Dorothy Marsh as a travel executive. Some material concerns her sister, Marjorie Marsh Enfield, her partner in Marsh Tours, Inc. Highlights of the collection include correspondence and reports from Dorothy's work as a Red Cross teacher in Budapest, 1925, and as Regional Director of Red Cross Service Clubs during World War II. There is a wealth of material on Marsh Tours, Inc., as well as some on the New York Women's Council and International Executive Service Corps. The photographs in Series I include images of Dorothy and her sister, Marjorie Marsh Enfield; Marsh Tours parties in various countries from, circa 1928-59; the Marsh Tours' Paris office; and American Red Cross activities (one with General De Gaulle during World War II).
This collection is organized into two series:
BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
Dorothy Marsh (Smith College class of 1921) donated her papers to the Sophia Smith Collection from 1971 to 1977.
Marsh, Dorothy, 1899-1979; International Executive Service Corps-History; Marsh Tours, Inc. (New York, N.Y.)-History-Sources; New York Women's Council-History; Businesswomen-United States-Biography-Sources; Tourism-United States-History-20th century-Sources; Travel agents-United States-Biography-Sources; Women owned business enterprises-United States-History; Women travelers-History-20th century-Sources; World War, 1939-1945-War work-Red Cross; World War, 1939-1945-Women-Personal narratives, American; Europe-Description and travel-Sources; Budapest (Hungary)-Description and travel-Sources
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
  - Contents (Box 1)
  - Biographical writings, 1945-73 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Obituary, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Passports, 1941-76 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Articles written by Marsh, 1929-68 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Articles about Dorothy and Marjorie Marsh, circa 1915-70 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Memorabilia: invitations, maps, menus and miscellaneous items, 1929-74 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous articles, 1924-72 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Awards, 1885-1946 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - New York State Distinguished Achievement Award, "Salute to Women": programs and correspondence, 1962-66 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Awards: American Society of Travel Agents Rosenbluth award, 1973-75 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Photographs 1911(?)-70 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence
    - To Dorothy Marsh (largely professional), 1915-76 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - From Dorothy Marsh (Marsh Tours and miscellaneous), 1948-71 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Miscellaneous, 1923-67 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- SERIES II. PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES
  - Employment agreements and miscellaneous documents, 1923-45 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Paris American Players: correspondence, 1929-72 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - American Red Cross, World War II
    - Correspondence, 1942-46 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Reports (Casablanca, Capri, South France, Overseas task force), 1943-45 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Playground course, Hungary (Ligue des Societes de la Croix - Rouge)
      - Correspondence, 1924-26 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Introductory speech, lesson plans and final report, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Manual (in Hungarian), 1925 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - American Women's Club of Paris: letters to Dorothy Marshy (house manager), 1927 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - New York Women's Council
    - Correspondence
      - From Marsh, 1959-69 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - To Marsh (including Nelson Rockefeller and Jane Todd), 1959-69 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Pamphlets, reports, newsletters and miscellaneous items, 1959-1969 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - VIP Tour 1965
      - Correspondence, 1964-66 (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
      - Itineraries, publicity and miscellaneous correspondence (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Florence Floods: Travel Industry Relief Fund
    - Correspondence
      - From Dorothy Marsh, 1966-67 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      - To Dorothy and Marjorie Marsh, 1966-67 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Publicity and miscellaneous correspondence, 1966-67 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - International Executive Service Corps
    - Pamphlets, articles and news, 1967-72 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1971-75 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Malaysia
      - Correspondence, 1971-72 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Reports, articles and pamphlets, 1964-75 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Thailand
      - Correspondence and mementos, 1970-72, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - Reports, pamphlets, and articles, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Marsh Tours, Inc.
    - Itineraries, 1941-68 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Business tours, 1959-64 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Profit sharing plan and insurance, 1961-65 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Promotion, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Traveling information, 1951-67 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Spring vacation tours, 1955-67 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Staff meetings, memoranda, and instructions, 1951-65 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Pamphlets, 1929-68 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Dorothy Marsh's personal pamphlets, 1948-68 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Theatre tours, 1933-74 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Workshop in international understanding, 1949-77 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - American Society of Travel Agents Inc. (ASTA)
    - Miscellaneous, 1962-76 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Southwest chapter meeting, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Pamphlets and list of members, June 1951 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - "A Pictorial Record of the 21st Annual Convention of the American Society of Travel Agents, Paris, October 21st-27th, 1951", 1951 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - South Africa picture book, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous pamphlets, 1948-73 (Box 4, Folder 15)